Inventory of the Mary C. Rixford papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Mary C. Rixford papers
1914-1922
XX669
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Collection relates to Allied propaganda, primarily British, during World War I, and to medical aspects of the war, especially activities of the American Red Cross
Rixford, Mary C.
Access
The collection is open for research
Access to audiovisual materials requires at least two weeks advance notice. Audiovisual materials include sound recordings, video recordings, and motion picture film. Hoover staff will determine whether use copies of the materials requested can be made available. Some materials may not be accessible even with advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
Collection relates to Allied propaganda, primarily British, during World War I, and to medical aspects of the war, especially activities of the American Red Cross.
Collection includes propaganda materials relating to military operations and home front conditions in many countries, especially Great Britain and Germany, during World War I. Pamphlets depict economic conditions in Germany during and immediately after World War I, especially food rationing, procurement of raw materials and war loan drives. Also includes German atrocities in France and Belgium, as well as work of the Committee on Alleged German Outrages.
Collection also includes pamphlets and monographs from Russian, Italian, Romanian, Turkish, Irish, and other sources.
Arranged by country, and therewith alphabetically by title. Some materials are placed in folders.
Related Material
World War I subject collection, 1914-2002, Hoover Institution Archives Payson J. Treat papers, 1855-1973, Hoover Institution Archives William C. Moore collection, 1914-1917, Hoover Institution Archives Price family papers, 1855-2004, Hoover Institution Archives
American National Red Cross.; International relief.; Propaganda, American.; Propaganda, British.; World War, 1914-1918--Economic aspects.; World War, 1914-1918--Food question.; World War, 1914-1918--Germany.; World War, 1914-1918--Medical care.; World War, 1914-1918--Prisoners and prisons.; World War, 1914-1918--Propaganda.; World War, 1914-1918--Supplies.
- British materials, 1914-1917 (Box 1)
  - After Twelve Months of War, C. F. G. Masterman (formerly Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster and a Member of the British Cabinet), Darling and Son, Limited, London, 1915
  - After Two Years, Hodder and Stoughton, London, New York, Toronto, 1916
  - The Attitude Of Great Britain In The Present War, James Bryce (Viscount Bryce), author of The Holy Roman Empire, The American Commonwealth, and other titles, formerly Ambassador to the United States, Macmillan and Co., Limited, London, 1916
  - The Battle of Jutland, John Buchan, Thomas Nelson and Sons, Ltd., London, New York, Paris, circa 1917
  - Black List and Blockade: Interview with the Rt. Hon. Lord Robert Cecil, M.P., in reply to the Swedish Prime Minister, London: Eyre and Spottiswoode, Ltd., London, 1916
  - Britain versus Germany: An Open Letter to Professor Eduard Meyer, Ph.D., L.L.D., of the University of Berlin (author of England, Her National and Political Evolution, and the War with Germany), Right Honorable J. M. Robertson, (author of The Evolution of States, War and Civilization, The Germans. etc.), T. Fisher Unwin, Ltd., London, 1917
  - Britain's Financial Effort, Hodder and Stoughton, London, New York, Toronto, 1917
  - Britain's Part In The War, Edward Cook, printed for The Victoria League by Wyman and Sons, Ltd., London, 1916
  - British Blockade, A. J. Balfour, Darling and Son, Limited, London, 1915
  - British Blockade: What It Means, How It Works, Stanhope W. Sprigg, printed by George Binney Dibblee, Windsor House, Bream's Buildings, circa 1917
  - British Commonwealth of Nations, a speech made by General Smuts on May 15th, 1917, Hodder and Stoughton, London, New York, Toronto
  - British Finance and Prussian Militarism. Two Interviews, Hodder and Stoughton, London, New York, Toronto, 1917
  - British Share In The War, H. A. L. Fisher, Thomas Nelson and Sons, London, circa 1916
  - British Staying Power: Lord Revelstoke's Views. Anglo-American Sympathies, interview given to the United Press of America, Sir Joseph Causton and Sons Limited, 1916
  - British War Aims: Statement by The Right Honourable David Lloyd George, January Fifth, Nineteen Hundred and Eighteen, authorized Version as published by The British Government, New York: George H. Doran Company
  - British Workman Defends His Home, Will Crooks, printed in Great Britain by The Whitwell Press, London, 1917
  - Case of the Allies: Being the Replies to President Wilson, and Mr. Balfour's Despatch, Hayman, Christy and Lilly, Ltd., London, 1917
  - Character of The British Empire, Ramsay Muir, Constable and Company Limited, London, 1917
  - Cotton Contraband, Viscount Milner, Darling and Son, Limited, London, 1915
  - Does the British Navy Take Prisoners? Printed in Great Britain by Darling and Son, Ltd., 1915
  - England and Her Critics, Mario Borsa, T. Fisher Unwin, Ltd., London, 1917
  - Finances of Great Britain and Germany, E. F. Davies, T. Fisher Unwin, Ltd., London, circa 1917
  - The Fourth of July in London, printed in Great Britain by Darling and Son, Ltd., London, 1917
  - A Free Europe: Being an Interview With the Rt. Hon. Sir Edward Grey, Bart., K.G., British Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs by Edward Price Bell (of The Chicago Daily News), T. Fisher Unwin, Ltd., London, 1916
  - Free Future For The World: A Speech by the Rt. Hon. H. H. Asquith, Prime Minister at The Guildhall on the 9th November, 1916, T. Fisher Unwin, Ltd., London
  - Freedom Of The Seas: Interview Given By the Rt. Hon. Arthur J. Balfour, M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty, Sir Joseph Causton and Sons, Limited, London, 1916
  - Freedom of the Seas, by the Hon. Bernhard R. Wise, K.C., Agent-General for New South Wales in London, London, Darling and Son, Limited, 1915
  - Great Britain and the European Crisis: Correspondence, and Statements in Parliament, Together With An Introductory Narrative of Events, printed under the authority of His majesty Stationery office by Hayman, Christy and Lilly, Ltd., London, 1914
  - Great Britain's Measures Against German Trade, a speech delivered by the Rt. Hon. Sir E. Grey, Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, in the House of Commons, on the 26th January, 1916, Hodder and Stoughton, London, New York, Toronto
  - "Great Britain's Sea Policy: A Reply To an American Critic", Reprinted from The Atlantic Monthly Gilbert Murray, T. Fisher Unwin, Ltd., London, 1917
  - How Britain Strove for Peace: A Record of Anglo-German Negotiations 1898-1914, Told From Authoritative Sources, Macmillan and Co., Edward Cook, Limited, London
  - How Do We Stand To-Day? A speech delivered by the Right Hon. H. H. Asquith, Prime Minister of the House of Commons, on the second November, 1915, T. Fisher Unwin, Ltd., London
  - How Long Will It Last? Reprinted From The New York Tribune of the 3rd May, 1916, Jas. Truscott and Son, Ltd., London
  - If The British Fleet Had Not Moved! Archibald Hurd, Darling and Son, Limited, 1915
  - If There Were No Navies! Archibald Hurd, Jas. Truscott and Son, Ltd., London, 1916
  - International Law and Autocracy: A Public Lecture Delivered Before The University of Pennsylvania by Geoffrey G. Butler, M.A., Fellow and Librarian of Corpus Christ College, Cambridge, Hodder and Stoughton, London, New York, Toronto, 1917
  - International Law and the Blockade, W. E. Hume-Williams, (Recorder of the City of Norwich), Sir Joseph Causton and Sons, Limited, London, 1916
  - Jutland Battle by Two Who Took Part In It, Burrup, Mathieson and Sprague Ltd., London, 1916
  - A Lasting Peace: A Conversation Between X. (a Neutral) and Y. (an Englishman), G. W. Prothero (author of German Policy Before the War), Modder and Stoughton, London, New York, Toronto, circa 1916
  - The Law of Blockade, Maurice A. Low, M.A. (author of The American People, a Study in National Psychology, Great Britain and the War, The Freedom of the Sees, and other titles), Sir Joseph Caueton and Sons, Limited, London, 1916
  - League of Peace And a Free Sea, Julian Corberr, Hodder and Stoughton, London, New York, Toronto, circa 1916
  - Mare Liberum: The Freedom of the Seas, Ramsey Muir, Hodder and Stoughton, London, New York, Toronto, circa 1916
  - Means of Victory: A Speech delivered by The Rt. Hon. Edwin Montagu, M.P., Minister of Munitions, on the 15th August, 1916, with illustrations, T. Fisher Unwin, Ltd., London
  - Mercy-Workers..Of The War..: An Interview With the Hon. Arthur Stanley, C.B., M.P., Chairman of the British Red Cross Society, which appeared in the New York American and the International News Service Syndicate, Sir Joseph Causton and Sons, Limited, London, 1916
  - Naval Prospects in 1917, Archibald Hurd, Eyre and Spottiswoode, Limited, London
  - The Navy And The War by the Right Honorable, A.J. Balfour, First Lord of The Admiralty, (August, 1914 to August, 1915), A. J. Balfour, Darling and Son, Limited, London
  - Peace Terms of The Allies, J. W. Headlam, Richard Clay and Sons, Ltd., London, 1917
  - The Press Censorship: Interview Given by Sir Edward T. Cook to the Associated Press, Burrup, Mathieson and Sprague Ltd., London, 1916
  - Reprisals Against Prisoners of War: Correspondence between The International Red Cross Committee and The British Government, Sir Joseph Causton and Sons, Limited, London, 1916
  - Shrinking The Issue: A Letter To Dr. George Brandes by William Archer, Hodder and Stoughton, London, New York, Toronto, 1917
  - Six Of One And Half–A–Dozen Of The Other: A Letter to Mr. L. Simons of the Hague, William Archer, T. Fisher Unwin, Ltd., London, 1917
  - Spectre of Navalism, Julian Corbett, Darling and Son, Limited, London, 1915
  - Strong Words From Mr. Redmond: Treason To The Home Rule Cause, Sir Joseph Causton and Sons, Limited, London, 1916
  - Thoughts On The War, from The Times Literary Supplement, A. Clutton-Brock, Methuen and Co. Ltd., London, 1914
  - Torpedoed, British and Foreign Sailor's Society, Inc., London, 1918
  - Treatment of Prisoners of War in England and Germany during the First Eight Months of the War, printed under the authority of His Majesty's Stationery Office by Harrison and Sons, London, 1915
  - Two Years Of War: By the Right Hon. Sir Gilbert Parker, interview with the Associated Press of the United States of America, Burrup Mathieson and Sprague, Ltd., London, 1916
  - The Union of Two Great Peoples, A Speech by W. H. Page, LL.D., American Ambassador to England, delivered at Plymouth, August 4th, 1917, Hoddeer and Stoughton, London, New York, Toronto
  - The United States and The War, reprinted from the Westminster Gazette, Gilbert Murray, W. Speaight and Sons, London, 1916
  - The United States and This War: A Word in Season, speech delivered by Sir Gilbert Parker, M.P., to the Pilgrims' Society, at the Savoy Hotel, London, on the 15th April, 1915, on the occasion of the 50th Anniversary of the Death of Abraham Lincoln, London, Darling and Son, Limited
  - Villain of the World-Tragedy: A Letter to Professor Ulrich V. Wilamowitz Möllendorf, William Archer, T. Fisher Unwin, Ltd., London, 1916 December 8
  - The War: Its Causes And Its Message, speeches delivered by the Prime Minister, August-October 1914, dedicated to the King by His Majesty's Gracious Permission, Methuen and Co. Ltd., London
  - The War: What Is England Doing? By Philosophus (an English Ranchman in New Mexico, U.S.), Jas. Truscott and Son, Ltd., 1916
  - What Is The Matter With England? Criticism And Reply, Gilbert Parker, Darling and Son, Limited, London, 1915
  - When The War Will End: Mr. Lloyd George's Speech At Glasgow, 29 June, 1917. Printed in Great Britain by Hayman, Christy and Lilly, Ltd., London
  - Why The Allies Will Win: As Interview With the Rt. Hon. D. Lloyd George, Minister of Munitions, published by The Daily Chronicle, London, circa 1916
  - World's Largest Loan, T. Fisher Unwin, Ltd., London, 1917
  - Zamora (Part Cargo Ex): Report of the Argument before Lord Parker of Waddington, Lord Sumner, Lord Parmoor, Lord Wrenbury, and Sir Arthur Channell, On The Hearing of The Appeal From the Judgment of Sir Samuel Evans, In the Above Case, and The Judgment of The Board, delivered by Lord Parker, reprinted from The Times Law Reports by permission of The Times Publishing Co., Ltd., by Sir Joseph Causton and Sons, Ltd., 1916
  - Other British materials, 1916 - 1917 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - Care Of The Dead, Eyre and Spottiswoode, Ltd., London, 1916
    - Frightfulness in Retreat, Hodder and Stoughton, London, New York, Toronto, 1917
    - War on Hospital Ships: From the Narratives of Eye-witnesses, T. Fisher Unwin, Ltd., London, 1917
- American materials, 1914-1922 (Box 1)
  - American Red Cross printed materials, 1916 - 1918
    - American Red Cross, Division Headquarters, First Aid Instruction Classes, November 1, 1917 (Box-folder 1: 1)
      Scope and Contents note
      Includes maps. Keep folder labeled 1:1 towards the back of the manuscript box for support of the materials.
    - American Red Cross (ARC) pamphlets, 1916 - 1918 (Box-folder 1: 2)
      - Regulations Governing the Employment of the American Red Cross in Time of War, Washington, Government Printing Office, 1917
      - Regulations of the National Committee on Red Cross Medical Service, revised February 20, 1917
      - Report of the National Committee on Red Cross Medical Service, American Medical Association, Chicago, circa 1917
      - American Red Cross, Department of Chapters, Organization of Committees for Development of Red Cross Instruction, revised April 30, 1917
      - Department of Military Relief, Bureau of Medical Service, Ambulance Companies, revised March 31, 1917
      - Department of Military Relief, Bureau of Medical Service, First Aid Division, 1917
      - Department of Military Relief, Bureau of Red Cross Supply Service, April 5, 1917
      - Department of Military Relief, Red Cross Sanitary Training Detachments, February 4, 1918
      - Department of Military Relief, Red Cross Base Hospital Units, 1916-1917
      - Department of Military Relief, Department of Military Relief, March 28, 1916
      - Department of Military Relief, Red Cross Sanitary Training Detachments, 1916, 1918
      - Bureau of Nursing Service, Instruction for Nurses Called Upon for Active Service, revised, 1917
      - Bureau of Nursing Service, Circular of Information Concerning the Courses in Elementary Hygiene and Home Care of the Sick, Home Dietetics, Preparation of Surgical Dressings, March 10, 1917
      - Nursing Service, Information for Applicants, 1916-1917
      - Instruction for Nurses Called Upon For Service in Military Hospitals, circa 1917
  - Americans of German Origin and The War, Otto Kahn, extracts from an address before The Merchants Association of New York at its Liberty Loan Meeting, June 1, 1917
  - The Balfour Visit: How America Received Her Distinguished Guest: And The Significance of The Conferences In The United States In 1917, edited by Charles Hanson Towne, New York, George H. Doran Company
  - British-American Adventures Toward Liberty, by Ralph W. Page, and Britain, Mother of Colonies, by Poultney Bigelow, reprinted from The World's Work, Library of War Literature, new York, 1918
  - Conflict For Human Liberty, Viscount Grey, New York, George H. Doran Company, circa 1917
  - The Days Of A Man: Being Memories of a Naturalist, Teacher, and Minor Prophet of Democracy, 1851-1921, World Book Company, Yonkers-on-Hudson, New York, 1922
    Biography of David Starr Jordan
  - Dead Lands of Europe, J. W. Headlam, New York, George H. Doran Company, circa 1917
  - Economic Weapon: In the War Against Germany, A. E. Zimmern, New York, George H. Doran Company, circa 1917
  - The Fate of Our Wounded in The Next War, by Jacob Frank, A.M., M.D., F.A.C.S., Lieutenant-Colonel, Surgeon-General of Illinois, First Lieutenant, Medical Reserve Corps, U.S. Army Consulting Surgeon Cook County, Michael Reese and German Hospitals, Ex-President Chicago Medical Society, Ex-President Chicago Surgical Society, President Association of Military Surgeons of the State of Illinois, Corresponding Member Sociedad Medica Pedro Escabedo, Mexico, Life Member Japanese Red Cross, Chicago, 1916 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - General Smuts's Message to South Wales, speech delivered at Tonypandy, Rhondda, on October 29, 1917, New York, George H. Doran Company
  - Hotchkiss School, Announcements and Regulations, 1915
  - Judicial Settlement of International Dispute, No. 17, Justice Between Nations by Simeon E. Baldwin, M. A., LL. D., Governor of Connecticut, Director of the Bureau of Comparative Law of the American Bar Association, formerly Chief Justice of Connecticut, and President of the American Political Science Association, the American Historical Association, the International Law Association, August 1914. Published quarterly by the American Society for Judicial Settlement of International Disputes, Baltimore, U.S.A.
  - League of Nations After Two Years, by Raymond B. Fosdick, formerly Under Secretary of the League of Nations, reprinted from The Atlantic Monthly through the courtesy of the Editor, issued by League of Nations New Bureau, New York, circa 1922
  - Lessons of the Great War: Presidential Address delivered at the Twenty-fourth Annual Meeting of the Association of Military Surgeons of the United States by Jefferson R. Kean, Colonel, Medical Corps, United States Army, reprinted from the Military Surgeon, October 1915
  - Militant American Journalism, Editorials, reprinted from The New York Herald, circa 1917
  - My Mission to London, 1912-1914: Revelations of The Last German Ambassador In England, Prince Lichnowsky (with preface by Professor Gilbert Murray), New York, George H. Doran Company, circa 1916
  - Peace: How To Get and Keep It, by Harry Gosling, C.H., J.P., L.C.C., President of the British Trade Union Congress, 1916; President of the Transport Workers' Federation, 1917, New York, George H. Doran Company, circa 1917
  - Plain Words From America: A Letter to a German Professor by Professor Douglas W. Johnson, Columbia University, New York, Hodder and Stoughton, London, New York, Toronto, 1917
  - Present Conditions in Europe, an address delivered before the San Francisco Chamber of Commerce and the San Francisco Commercial Club, Thursday, July 13, 1922, by Cyrus Peirce of Cyrus Peirce and Company
  - President's Address before the Ohio State Medical Association, June 1920 by J. F. Baldwin. A. M., M. D., F. A.C.S., Columbus, Ohio (Surgeon-in-chief to Grant Hospital, Consulting Surgeon Children's Hospital, etc.), 1921
  - Prussianized Germany: Americans of Foreign Descent and America's Cause, Otto Kahn, from the address before the Harrisburg, Pennsylvania, Chamber of Commerce, September 20, 1917
  - Report of the Secretary of the War Work Council, delivered at the Annual Meeting, June 18, 1918, YMCA
  - Romance of Air-Fighting, Wherry R. Anderson, New York, George H. Doran Company, circa 1917 (Box 2)
  - Siam Revisited, Cornelius Beach Bradley, reprint from the University of California Chronicle, Vol. XII, No. 2, circa 1917
  - Some Fundamental Considerations Affecting The Food Supply of The United States: Memorandum Prepared for the Committee on Resources and Food Supply of the State Council of Defense, by Thomas Forsyth Hunt, University of California Press, Berkeley, College of Agriculture, circular No. 163, 1917
  - Some Gains of the War: An Address to the Royal Colonial Institute, delivered February Thirteen, Nineteen Hundred and Eighteen, Walter Raleigh, New York, George H, Doran Company, 1915
  - The Tanks (By Request, and With Permission), by Colonel E.D. Swinton, C.B., D.S.O., Royal Engineers, reprinted from The World's Work, New York, George H. Doran Company, circa 1917
  - Universal Obligation to Service, The Only Fair, Equitable, Democratic Way To Raise An Army In Republic Like Ours, speech of Hon. Julius Kahn of California in the House of Representatives, Friday, April 27, 1917, Washington, Government Printing Office
  - Vignettes from Siamese Legend and Life, Cornelius Beach Bradley, reprint from the University of California Chronicle, Vol. XIII, No. 4, circa 1917
  - A War of Liberation, New York, George H. Doran Company (published in America for Hodder and Stoughton), circa 1916
- French materials, 1915 (Box 2)
  - German Atrocities in France, a translation of the Official Report of the French Commission ( Journal Officiel de la République Française, January 8, 1915), published by authority (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Soul of France: Visits to Invaded Districts by Maurice Barrès, Membre de l'Académie française, T. Fisher Unwin, Ltd., London, 1915
  - Diplomatic Correspondence Respecting the War, published by the French Government: The European War, Documents Relating to the Negotiations Which Preceded Germany's Declaration of War on Russia (August 1, 1914), and on France (August 3, 1914), London, printed under the authority of His Majesty's Stationery Office by Harrion and Sons
- Belgian materials, 1914 - 1917 (Box 2)
  - Who Wanted War? The Origin of the War According to Diplomatic Documents, by É. Durkheim and E. Denis, Professors at the University of Paris, translated by A. M. Wilson-Garinei, Librarie Armand Colin, Paris, 1915
  - An Appeal to Truth: A Letter Addressed by Cardinal Mercier Archbishop of Malines, and the Bishops of Belgium, to the Cardinals, Archbishops and Bishops of Germany, Bavaria and Austria-Hungary, Hodder and Stoughton, London, New York, Toronto, 1915
  - Belgium and Greece, J. W. Headlam, Hodder and Stoughton, London, New York, Toronto, circa 1916
  - The Condition of the Belgian Workmen Now Refugees in England, T. Fisher Unwin, Ltd., 1917
  - The Deportations: Statement by the American Minister to Belgium, T. Fisher Unwin, Ltd., London, 1917
  - Diplomatic Correspondence Respecting The War Published by the Belgian Government, presented to both Houses of Parliament by Command of His Majesty, October 1914, London. Printed under the authority of His Majesty Stationery Office by Harrison and Sons
  - Memorandum of The Belgian Government of the Deportation and Forced Labour of the Belgian Civilian Population Ordered by The German Government, circa 1916
  - The Second Belgian Grey Book, part 1 and 2 (section 10). London, printed under the authority of his Majesty's Stationery Office by Darling and Son, Limited, 1915
  - A Signal of Distress: The Belgian Bishops to Public Opinion: The Story of the Belgian Deportations, London, Eyee and Spottiswoode, Limited, 1916
  - To Belgium, London, W. Speaight and Sons, 1916
  - The Violation By Germany of the Neutrality of Belgium and Luxemburg, by André Weiss, member of the Institut de France, Professor of international law in the University of Paris, translated by Walter Thomas, professor of English Literature in the University of Lyons, Studies and Documents on the War series, Librairie Armand Colin, Paris, 1915
- Italian materials, 1915, 1917 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Italy: Our Ally, Being an Account of the Visit to Italy of the Right Hon. H. H. Asquith, M.P., Prime Minister of Great Britain, T. Fisher Unwin, Ltd., circa 1915